<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods vvarning to His people of England, by the great overflowing of the waters or floudes lately hapned in South-Wales and many other places vvherein is declared the great losses and wonderfull damages that hapned thereby, by the drowning of many townes and villages to the vtter vndooing of many thousandes of people.</title>
            <author>Jones, William, of Usk.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10011.4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2616</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24384603</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24384603</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00013)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1850:57)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods vvarning to His people of England, by the great overflowing of the waters or floudes lately hapned in South-Wales and many other places vvherein is declared the great losses and wonderfull damages that hapned thereby, by the drowning of many townes and villages to the vtter vndooing of many thousandes of people.</title>
                  <author>Jones, William, of Usk.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Barley and Io. Bayly, and are to be solde in Gratious Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"By William Iones of Vske Gent."--Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Illustrated t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Floods --  Great Britain --  Religious aspects.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27603:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27603:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GODS VVARNING TO HIS people of ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>BY THE GREAT OVERFLOWING OF THE Waters or Floudes lately hapned in <hi>South-wales,</hi> and many other places.</p>
            <p>VVherein is declared the great loſſes, and wonderfull da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, that hapned thereby: by the drowning of many Townes and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, to the vtter vndooing of many thouſandes of people.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>At London printed for W. Barley, and Io. Bayly, and are to be ſolde in Gratious ſtreet. 1607.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:27603:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27603:2"/>
            <head>Gods Warning to his people of England.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ANY are the dombe</hi> warninges of Diſtruction, which the Almighty God hath lately ſcourged this our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with; And many more are the threatning Tokens, of his heauy wrath extended toward vs: All which in blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hearts, may inforce vs to put on the true garment of Repentance, and like vnto the <hi>Niniuits,</hi> vnfainedly ſolicite the ſwéet mercies of our moſt louing God: Therefore let vs now call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the late grieuous and moſt lamentable Plague of Peſtilence, wherein the wrath of God tooke from vs ſo many thouſandes of our friendes, kindred and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance: let vs alſo call to remembraunce the moſt wicked and pretended malice, of the late Papiſticall Conſpiracie of Traytors, that with powder practiſed the ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on of this beautifull Kingdome: And laſtly let vs fix our eyes vpon theiſe late ſwellinges of the outragious Waters, which of late now hapned in diuers partes of this Realme, together with the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing of the Seas in diuers and ſundry places there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: whoſe fruitfull valeys, being now ouerwhelmed and drowned with thoſe moſt vnfortunate and vnſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſalt waters, doe fore-ſhew great Barrennes, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27603:3"/>
Famin to enſue after it (vnleſſe the Almightie God of his great infinit mercy and goodneſſe doe preuent it.) But now oh England, be not ouercome with thine own folly: Be not blinded with the ouermuch ſecuritie of the ſelfe, neyther ſinke thou thy ſelfe in thine owne ſinne: For ſince the generall diſſolution of the whole World by Water: in the time of <hi>Noy,</hi> neuer the like Invnda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or watry puniſhment then hapned now here rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to the great griefe of all Chriſtian hearers, as by this ſequell it ſhall heare appeare.</p>
            <p>Vpon Tueſday beeing the 20. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> laſt paſt, 1607. in diuers places aſwell in the Weſterne partes of <hi>England,</hi> as alſo in diuers other places of the this Realme: there hapned ſuch an ouerflowing of Waters, ſuch a violent ſwelling of the Seas, and ſuch forcible breaches made into the firme Land. namely into the boſomes of theſe countries following. That is to ſay, in the Counties of <hi>Gloceſter, Sommerſet,</hi> together with the Counties of <hi>Munmoth, Glamorgan, Carma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>then,</hi> and diuers and ſundry other places of <hi>South-wales.</hi> the like neuer in the memory of man, hath euer bin ſeene or heard of: The ſuddaine terror whereof ſtrooke ſuch an amazed feare into the hearts of all the inhabitantes, of thoſe partes, that euery one prepared himſelfe ready to entertaine the laſt Period of his liues Deſtruction: Déeming it altogether to be a ſecond deluge: or an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall, puniſhment by Water.</p>
            <p>For vpon the Tueſday beeing the 20. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> laſt, as aforeſaid, about nine of the clocke in the Morning, the Sunne being moſt fairely and brightly ſpred, many of the Inhabitantes of thoſe Countreys before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, prepared themſelues to their affayres, ſome to one buſines, ſome to an other: euery man according to his calling. As the Plowmen ſetting foorth their cattle to their labours, the Shepheardes féeding of their flockes, the Farmers ouer-ſéeing of their grounds, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27603:3"/>
looking to their Cattle féeding therein, and ſo euery on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> imploid in his buſines, as occaſion required. Then they might ſée and perceiue a far of, as it were in the Element, huge and mighty Hilles of water, tumbling one ouer another, in ſuch ſort as if the greateſt moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes in the world, had ouerwhelmed the lowe Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leyes or Marſhy grounds. Sometimes it ſo dazeled the eyes of many of the Spectators, that they imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined it had bin ſome fogge or miſte, comming with great ſwiftnes towardes them, and with ſuch a ſmoke, as if Mountaines were all on fire: and to the view of ſome it ſeemed as if Myllions of thouſands of Arrowes had bin ſhot foorth all at one time, which came in ſuch ſwiftneſſe, as it was verily thought, that the Fowles of the Ayre could ſcarſe fly ſo faſt, ſuch was the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning furyes thereof.</p>
            <p>But aſſoone as the people of thoſe Countries, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that it was the violence of the Waters of the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Seas, and that they began to exceede the compaſſe of their accuſtomed boundes, and making ſo furiouſly towardes them: happy were they that could make the beſt, and moſt ſpéed away, many of them, leauing all their goods and ſubſtance, to the mercyleſſe Waters, béeing glad to eſcape away with life themſelues: But ſo violent and ſwift were the outragious waues, that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued one an other, with ſuch vehemencie, and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters multiplying ſo much in ſo ſhort a time, that in leſſe then fiue houres ſpace, moſt part of thoſe cuntreys (and eſpecially the places which lay lowe,) were all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowen and many hundreds of people both men wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and children were then quite deuoured, by theſe outragious Waters, ſuch was the furie of the Waues, of the Seas, the one of them dryuing the other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes with ſuch force and ſwiftnes that it is almoſt incredible for any to beleeue the ſame, except ſuch as taſted of the ſmart thereof; and and ſuch as beheld the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27603:4"/>
ſame, with their eyes: Nay more, the Farmers, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, and Shepheards, might beholde their goodly flockes of Sheepe, ſwimming vpon the Waters dead, which could by no meanes be recouered.</p>
            <p>Many Gentlemen, Yeamen and others, had great loſſes, of cattle, as Oxen, Kine, Bullockes, Horſes, Colts, Sheepe, Swine, Nay not ſo much as their poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try about their houſes, but all were ouerwhelmed and drownd, by theſe merciles Waters: Many men that were rich in the morning when they roſe out of their beds, were made poore before noone the ſame day: ſuch are the Iudgements of the Almightie God, who is the geuer of all good thinges, who can and will diſpoſe of them agayne at all times, according to his good will and pleaſure, whenſoeuer it ſhall ſéeme beſt vnto him. Many others likewiſe, had their habitations or dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſes all carryed away in a ſhort time, and had not a place left them, ſo much as to ſhrowde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, many that had great ſtore of Corne and Grayne, in their Barnes and Garners in the morning had not within fiue houres ſpace afterwardes, ſo much as one Grayne to make them bread withall: Neither had they ſo much left as a locke of Hay or Straw to fede their cattell which were left: Such was the great miſery they ſuſteyned by the fury of this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Element, from which like, good Lord I beſéech him of his infinite mercy and goodnes to deliuer vs all.</p>
            <p>The names of ſome of the Townes and Villages which ſuffered great harmes and loſſes hereby were theſe. <hi>(Viz.)</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Briſtoll</hi> and <hi>Auſt,</hi> this <hi>Auſt</hi> is a village or town ſome 8 miles diſtant from <hi>Briſtoll</hi> vpon the Seauerne ſide where all people are Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed ouer, that come out of <hi>Wales,</hi> into thoſe partes of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> and <hi>Sommerſett-ſhire.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:27603:4"/>All the countries along on both the ſides of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of <hi>Seauerne,</hi> from <hi>Glouceſter</hi> to <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome 20. miles was all ouerflowne, in ſome places 6. miles ouer, in ſome places more, in ſome leſſe.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, all or the moſt parte, of the Bridges, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene <hi>Glouceſter</hi> and <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> were all forcibly carted away with the Waters: beſides many goodly buildings there abouts much defaced, and many of them carryed quite away: beſides many other great loſſes of al kinde of Corne and Grayne, and cattle that were then loſt.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Auſt,</hi> many paſſengers that are Ferryed ouer there now, are faine to be guided by guides, all along the Cauſies, where the water ſtill remayneth for the ſpace of 3 or 4 myles, or elſe they wilbe in great daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Drowning, the Water lyeth as yet ſo déepe there.</p>
            <p>Many dead Carkaſſes, both there, and in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, of the country, are dayly found floating vpon the Waters, and as yet cannot be knowne who they are, or what number of perſons are drowned, by reaſon of the ſame Waters, which as yet in many places remaine very déepe: ſo great was the ſpoyle that thiefe mercileſſe Elementes there wrought and made.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Briſtoll</hi> was much harme done, by the ouerflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Waters, but not ſo much as in other places, many Cellars and Ware-houſes, where great ſtore of Marchandize was in, (as Wine, Salt, hope, Spices, and other ſuch like Ware) were all ſpoyled. And the people of the Towne were inforced to be carried in Boates, vp and downe the ſaid Cittie about their buſines in the Fayre time there.</p>
            <p>Vpon the other ſide of the Riuer of <hi>Seauerne,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes a Towne called <hi>Chepſtow,</hi> vpon the lower groundes, was much harme done, by the vyolence of the Water,</p>
            <p>There was in <hi>Chepſtow</hi> a woman drown'd in her
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27603:5"/>
bed: and alſo a Gyrle, by the like miſfortune.</p>
            <p>Alſo, all along the ſame coaſtes, do to <hi>Gold-clyft, Matherne, Callicot-Moores, Redrift, Newport, Cardiffe, Cowbridge, Swanſey, Laugherne, Llanſtephan,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other places, of <hi>Glamorgan-ſhire, Munmoth-ſhire, Carmarthen-ſhire,</hi> and <hi>Cardigan-ſhire:</hi> many great harmes were there done, and the Waters raged ſo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, and with ſuch great vehemencie, that it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that in thoſe partes, there cannot be ſo fewe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons drowned as 500. both Men, Women and Children, beſides the loſſe of aboundance of all kinde of Corne and Graine: together with their Hay, and other prouiſion which they had made for their Cattle.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, there were in the places afore mentioned, many thouſandes of Cattle, which were feeding in the lowe Valeyes, drown'd and ouerwhelmed with the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of the furious Waters: as Oxen, Kine, young Beaſtes, Horſes, Sheeps, Swine, and ſuch like, the number is deemed infinit: yea, and not ſo much as Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kies, Hens, Geeſe, Duckes, and other Poultry about their houſes, could once eſcape away, the Waues of the Sea ſo ouerwhelmed them.</p>
            <p>And that which is more ſtraunge: There are not now found onely floating vpon the waters ſtill remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the dead Carkaſſes of many men women and children: But alſo an aboundance of all kinde of wilde Beaſtes, as Foxes, Hares, Conyes, Rats, Moules and ſuch like: ſome of them ſwimming one vpon an others backe, thinking to haue ſaued themſelues thereby, but all was in vaine. ſuch was the force of the waters that ouer-preſſed them.</p>
            <p>In a place in <hi>Munmoth-ſhire,</hi> there was a maide went to milke her Kine in the morning, but before ſhe had fully ended her buſines the vehemencie of the waters increaſed, and ſo ſuddenly enuironed her about, that ſhe could not eſcape thence, but was enforced to make ſhift
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27603:5"/>
vp to the top of an high Banke to ſaue her ſelfe, which ſhe did with much adoe, where ſhe was conſtrained to abide all that day and night, vntill 8 of the clocke in the next morning, in great diſtreſſe, what with the coldnes of the ayre and waters: and what with other Accidents that there hapned vnto her, ſhe had bin like there to haue periſhed: had not the Almightie God of his infinit mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and goodnes, preſerued her, from ſuch great perills and daungers, which were likely there to enſue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her.</p>
            <p>But there placing her ſelfe for ſaueguard of her life as aforeſaid, hauing none other refuge to fly vnto: the Waters in ſuch violent ſort had ſo purſued her, that there was but a ſmall diſtance of ground left vncouered with Waters, for her to abide vpon: There ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned moſt pittyfully lamenting the great daunger of life that ſhe was then in, expecting euery minute of an houre, to be ouerwhelmed with thoſe mercyleſſe Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: But the Almighty God, who is the Creator of all good things, when he thought méete, ſent his holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell to commaund the Waters to ceaſe their fury: and to returne into their accuſtomed bounds againe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by according to his moſt bleſſed will and pleaſure ſhe was then preſerued.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſpace, during the continuance of her abode there, diuers of her friends practiſed all the means they could to recouer her, but could not, the Waters were of ſuch a déepenes about her, and Boates they had none, in all thoſe partes to ſuccour her, ſuch was their want in this diſtreſſe, that many periſhed through the want thereof.</p>
            <p>There was a Gentleman of worth, dwelling néere vnto the place where ſhe was, who cauſed a goodly Gelding to be ſadled, and ſet a man vpon the backe of him, thinking to haue fetcht her away, but ſuch were the déepenes of the waters, that he durſt not aduenture
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27603:6"/>
the ſame retyred.</p>
            <p>At laſt ſome of his friends, deuiſed a deuiſe, and tyed two broad troughes the one to the other, (ſuch as in thoſe countreys they vſe to ſalt Bacon in) and put ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two luſtie ſtrong men, who with long Powles (ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring theſe troughes (as if they had bin Boates) made great ſhift to come to her, and ſo by this meanes, through Gods good helpe ſhe was then ſaued.</p>
            <p>But now (gentle Reader) marke what befell, at this time, of the ſtrangenes of other creatures: whom the Waters had violently oppreſſed: for the two men which tooke vpon them to fetch away the Maide from the top of the Banke, can truely witneſſe the ſame as well as her ſelfe to be true, for they beheld the ſame with their Eyes.</p>
            <p>The Hill or Banke where the Maide abode all that ſpace, was all ſo couered ouer, with wilde Beaſtes, and Vormin, that came thither to ſéeke for ſuccour, that ſhe had much adoe to ſaue her ſelfe, from taking of hurt by them: and much a-doe ſhe had to kéepe them from crée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vpon and about her, ſhe was not ſo much in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Water on the one ſide: as ſhe was troubled with theſe Vermin on the other ſide.</p>
            <p>The Beaſtes and Vermin that were there were theſe. <hi>(Viz)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dogs, Cats, Moules, Foxes, Hares, Conyes, yea and not ſo much, as Mice and Rats: but were there in abundance, and that which is more ſtraunge: The one of them neuer once offred to annoy the other: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were deadly enemies by Nature the one to another: Yet in this daunger of life, they not once offred to expreſſe their naturall enuie: But in a gentle ſort, they fréely inioyed the libertie of life, which in mine opinion, was a moſt wonderfull worke in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>But now let vs leaue this matter touching this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27603:6"/>
Maide, beſides the other accidentes before rehearſed and let vs returne againe to theſe watry miſeries: The counties of <hi>Glamorgan, Carmarthen</hi> and <hi>Cardigan,</hi> and many other places in <hi>South-wales,</hi> haue likewiſe borne the heauy burden, of Gods wrath herein: And many were the liues of them that were loſt through this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Many there were which fled into the tops of high trées, and there were inforced to abide ſome thrée daies, ſome more, and ſome leſſe, without any victuals at all, there ſuffring much colde beſides many other calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſome of them in ſuch ſort, that through ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much hunger and colde, ſome of them fell downe againe out of the Trées, and ſo were like to periſh, for want of ſuccour. Other ſome, ſate in the tops of high Trées as aforeſaid, beholding their wiues, children, and ſeruants, ſwimming (remediles of all ſuccour) in the Waters.</p>
            <p>Other ſome ſitting in the tops of Trees might beholde their houſes ouerflowne with the Waters: ſome their houſes caryed quite away: and no ſigne or token left there of them.</p>
            <p>Many of them might ſée, as they ſtood vpon the tops of high Hilles, their Cattle periſh, and could not tell how to ſuccour them, and their Barnes, with all their ſtore of Corne and Graine quite conſumed, which was no ſmall griefe vnto them,</p>
            <p>Many people and Cattle in diuers places of thoſe Cuntreys, might haue béene ſaued in time, if that the cuntreys had beene any thing like furniſhed with botes or other prouiſion fit for ſuch a ſudden Accident, as this was, which as God himſelfe knoweth, was little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of them, to haue fallen ſo ſuddenly vpon them.</p>
            <p>But ſéeing the cuntreys were ſo vnfurniſhed with Boates much harme was done, to the vtter vndooing of many thouſandes.</p>
            <p>Some fled into the tops of Churches and Stéeples,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27603:7"/>
to ſaue themſelues, from whence they might beholde, themſelues depriued aſwell of all their ſubſtance, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of al their ioys, which they had before receiued in their wiues and Children. Alſo whole Reekes of Peaſe, Beanes, Oates, and other graine were ſeene a far of, to float vpon the Water too and fro, in the Countreys as if they had bin ſhips vpon the Seas.</p>
            <p>The Foundations of many Churches and houſes, were in a manner decayed, and ſome caryed quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as in <hi>Cardiffe,</hi> in the county of <hi>Glamorgan</hi> there was a great part of the Church next the Water ſide ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten downe, with the Water, many houſes and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens there, which were neere the water ſide, were all ouerflowen, and much harme done.</p>
            <p>Diuers other Churches lie hidden in the Waters, and ſome of them the tops are to be ſeene: and other ſome, nothing at all to be ſéene, but the very tops of the Steeples, and of ſome of them nothing at all, neyther ſteeple nor nothing elſe. Alſo many ſchooles of young ſchollers, in many places of thoſe cuntreys, ſtood in great perplexitie, ſome of them aduenturing home to their parents were drowned by the way: Other ſome ſtaying behinde in in Churches, did climbe vp to the tops of Steeples, where they were very néere ſtarved to death for want of ſeede and fire: many by the help of boards and plankes of Wood, ſwam to dry land and ſo were preſerued from vntimely Death, Many had Boates brought them, ſome 10 miles, ſome 15, ſome 20. where there was neuer ſeene any Boates before.</p>
            <p>Thus God ſuffred many of them to eſcape his yrefull wrath, in hope of their amendment of life: Some men that were riding on the high wayes were ouertaken with theſe mercileſſe Waters, and were drowned.</p>
            <p>And againe many haue bin moſt ſtrangely preſerued.</p>
            <p>As for example, there was in the Countie of <hi>Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morgan,</hi> a man both blind and bedriden and one which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27603:7"/>
had not bin able to ſtand vpon his legs in ten yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he had his poore cottage broken downe by the force of the Waters, and himſelfe, Bed and all caryed into the open fields, where being readie to ſinke, and at the point to ſéeke a reſting place, two fathoms déepe vnder the Waters: his hand by chaunce catcht holde of the Ratter of an houſe ſwimming by the fierceneſſe of the Windes, then blowing Eaſternely he was driuen ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Land, and ſo eſcaped.</p>
            <p>Alſo in an other place, there was a man Child of the age, of 5. or 6. yeares, which was kept ſwimming for the ſpace of two houres, aboue the Waters, by reaſon that his long Coates lay ſpread vpon the tops of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and beeing at laſt, at the very poynt to ſinke: there came by chaunce by, (floating vpon the tops of the Waters,) a fat Weather that was dead, very full of Wooll: The poore diſtreſſed Child perceiuing this good meanes of recouerie, caught faſt hold on the Wethers Wool, and likewiſe with the winde he was driuen to dry land, and ſo ſaued.</p>
            <p>There was alſo in the County of <hi>Carmarthen,</hi> a young Woman, who had foure ſmall Children, and not one of them able to helpe it ſelfe: And the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſeeing the furyes of the Waters to be ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to ceaze vpon her, threatning the Deſtruction of her ſelfe and her ſmall Children, (and as a Womans wit is euer ready in extreamities) ſhe tooke along Trough, wherein ſhe was wont to make her bread in, and therein placed her ſelfe, and her foure Children: And ſo putting themſelues to the mercies of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, they were all by that meanes driuen to the dry land, and by Gods good prouidence thereby they were all ſaued.</p>
            <p>Many more there were that through the handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes of God were preſerued from this violent death of Drowning, ſome on the backes of dead Cattle:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27603:8"/>
ſome vpon Woodden plankes: Some by clyming of Trées: Some by remaining in the tops of high Stée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Churches, other ſome by making of ſpeede away with ſwift horſes, and ſome by the meanes of Boates, ſent out by their friendes to ſuccour them: but there were not ſo many ſo ſtraungely ſaued, but there were as many in number as ſtraungely drown'd.</p>
            <p>The lowe Marſhes and Feany groundes, néere <hi>Barſtable</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Deuon</hi> were ouerflowne, ſo farre out, and in ſuch outragious ſort, that the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey all along to <hi>Bridge-water,</hi> was greatly diſtreſſed thereby, and much hurt there done: it is a moſt pitiful fight to beholde what numbers of fat Oxen were there Drowned: what flockes of Shéepe, what heardes of Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, haue there bin loſt, and Drowned in theſe ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tragious Waters: there is little now remaining there, to be ſéene, but huge Waters like to the maine Ocean: The tops of Churches and Stéeples like to the tops of Rockes in the Sea, Great Réekes of fodder for cattle, are floating like Ships vpon the Waters, and dead Beaſtes ſwimming thereon: Now paſt feeding on the ſame, through the rigour of this Element of Water: The tops of Trées, a man may beholde remayning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Waters, Vppon whete Braunches, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of all kinde of Turkies, Hens, and other ſuch like Poultry were faine to fly vp into the Trées to ſaue their liues, where many of them periſhed to death, for want of reliefe, not béeing able to fly to dry land for ſuccour, by reaſon of their weakenes.</p>
            <p>This mercyleſſe Water breaking into the boſome of the firme Land, hath proued a fearefull puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as well to all other liuing Creatures: as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to all Mankinde: Which if it had not binne for the mercyfull promiſe of God, at the laſt diſſolution of the World, by Water, by the ſigne of the Raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowe,
<pb facs="tcp:27603:8"/>
which is ſtill ſhewed vs: wee might haue ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily beleeued, this time had bin the very houre of Chriſt his comming: From which Element of VVater, extended towardes vs in this fearefull manner, good Lord deliuer vs all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <byline>By William Iones of Vske Gent.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
